Katie **Spoon**

katherine.spoon@colorado.edu | 🎓 katiespoon.github.io

Research

I'm interested in identifying and describing inequalities in social systems, and designing, implementing, and evaluating interventions to address those inequalities. My research is broadly focused on quantifying barriers to and retention within the scientific and technical workforce for historically excluded populations. I enjoy using a diverse range of data science and social science methods to conduct large-scale, interdisciplinary administrative, survey, network, and text analyses, which often reveal patterns not visible at a smaller scale. My work is also informed by previous research and industry experience in machine learning, AI for social good, computer vision and natural language processing.

Education

2020 – **Ph.D.** in Computer Science

University of Colorado, Boulder

Advisors: Aaron Clauset & Dan Larremore

2022 — M.A. in Educational Foundations, Policy and Practice

Concentration: Evaluation & Policy Analysis

University of Colorado, Boulder

Advisor: Kevin Welner

2018 − 2019 **M.S.** in Computer Science

Indiana University, Bloomington Advisors: David Crandall & Katie Siek

Thesis: Detecting Dyslexia in Handwriting Using Neural Networks

2015 – 2019 **B.S.** in Computer Science, Minor: Math

Indiana University, Bloomington

Employment

June 2019 — Aug. 2020 Research Engineer

IBM Research, Artificial Intelligence Hardware Group (San Jose, CA)

Sep. 2017 — June 2019 Research Assistant

Indiana University Computer Vision Lab (Bloomington, IN)

Summer 2018 Research Intern

IBM Research, Artificial Intelligence Hardware Group (San Jose, CA)

Summer 2017 Research Intern

MIT Lincoln Laboratory, Machine Learning Group (Boston, MA)

Aug. 2016 — Sep. 2017 Software Development Team Lead

Indiana University Kelley School of Business (Bloomington, IN)

Summer 2016 Research Assistant

NSF Research Experience for Undergraduates (Bloomington, IN)

Honors & Awards

TIOTIOI D CITIVAL AD	
2021-2024	NSF Graduate Research Fellowship
	\$37,000/year and tuition for three years of graduate school in a STEM field.
2023	Publication Recognition Award
2020	\$500 award from the CU Boulder Computer Science department for "Gender
	and retention patterns among U.S. faculty"
2019	National Center for Women in Technology Collegiate Award
	\$10,000 award that "recognizes technical contributions to projects
	that demonstrate a high level of innovation and potential impact."
2019	Provost's Award for Undergraduate Research and Creative Activity
	Mathematics & Natural Sciences winner, one of five categories total.
	Recognizes "outstanding achievement in research by undergraduates."
2019	Teaching Assistant of the Year Runner-Up
	IU Luddy School of Informatics, Computing and Engineering
2019	Global Challenges Proposal, Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition
	Selected proposal, inaugural Global Challenges workshop (10% accept rate)
2019	Best Poster Award, International Conference on Machine Learning
	·, ·· · · · · · · · · · · · · · · · · ·

Grants

2015-2016

"Quantifying the origins and impacts of book bans in U.S. schools"
 PI, with Isabelle Langrock (co-PI), Jack LaViolette (co-PI) and Marcelo S.O. Goncalves (co-PI)
 Russell Sage Foundation & Social Science Research Council, \$1,500

Travel Funding: Summer Institute in Computational Social Science full travel funding (June 2022); CVPR Global Challenges Workshop full travel funding (June 2019); ICML AI for Social Good Workshop travel scholarship & registration fee waiver (June 2019); NCWIT annual conference full travel funding (May 2019); Grace Hopper Celebration of Women in Computing travel scholarship (Sep. 2016)

Emerging Research Scholar, Center of Excellence for Women & Technology

Publications

Journal Articles

2023 Gender and retention patterns among U.S. faculty [Pre-print]

K. Spoon, N. LaBerge, K. H. Wapman, S. Zhang, A. C. Morgan, M. Galesic, B. K. Fosdick, D. B. Larremore, and A. Clauset. *In Press, Science Advances*.

2021 Towards software-equivalent accuracy on transformer-based deep neural networks with analog memory devices [Paper]

K. Spoon, H. Tsai, A. Chen, M.J. Rasch, S. Ambrogio, C. Mackin, A. Fasoli, A. Friz, P. Narayanan, M. Stanisavljevic, and G.W. Burr. Frontiers in Computational Neuroscience.

Noise-resilient DNN: Tolerating noise in PCM-based AI accelerators via noise-aware training S. Kariyappa, H. Tsai, **K. Spoon**, S. Ambrogio, P. Narayanan, C. Mackin, A. Chen, M. Quereshi, and G.W. Burr. IEEE *Transactions on Electron Devices*.

Conference Papers

- 2021 Mushroom-type phase change memory with projection liner: An array-level demonstration of conductance drift and noise mitigation
 - R. L. Bruce, et al. [including K. Spoon]. IEEE International Reliability Physics Symposium (IRPS).
- Fully on-chip MAC at 14nm enabled by accurate row-wise programming of PCM-based weights and parallel vector-transport in duration-format
 - P. Narayanan, et al. [including K. Spoon]. Symposium on VLSI Technology.
- Neuromorphic computing with phase change, device reliability, and variability challenges C. Mackin, et al. [including **K. Spoon**]. IEEE International Reliability Physics Symposium (IRPS).
- 2019 Reducing the impact of phase-change memory conductance drift on the Inference of large-scale hardware neural networks
 - S. Ambrogio, M. Gallot, **K. Spoon**, H. Tsai, C. Mackin, M. Wesson, S. Kariyappa, P. Narayanan, C.C. Liu, A. Kumar, A. Chen, and G.W. Burr. 65th IEEE International Electron Devices Meeting (IEDM). Ranked 2nd/98 papers.

Workshop Papers

- 2020 Accelerating deep neural networks with analog memory devices
 - **K. Spoon**, S. Ambrogio, P. Narayanan, H. Tsai, C. Mackin, A. Chen, A. Fasoli, A. Friz, and G.W. Burr. *International Memory Workshop*.
- 2019 Can we (and should we) use AI to detect dyslexia in children's handwriting? [Paper]
 - K. Spoon, D. Crandall, K. Siek, and M. Fillmore. AI for Social Good Workshop, NeurIPS.
- 2019 Towards detecting dyslexia in children's handwriting using neural networks [Paper]
 - **K. Spoon**, D. Crandall, and K. Siek. AI for Social Good Workshop, *International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML)*.

Book Chapters

2022 Accelerating deep neural networks with analog memory devices

K. Spoon, S. Ambrogio, P. Narayanan, H. Tsai, C. Mackin, A. Chen, A. Fasoli, A. Friz and G.W. Burr. In *Machine Learning & Non-Volatile Memories*. Ed. C. Zambelli, Springer.

Talks

Quantifying the origins and impacts of book bans in U.S. schools International Conference on Computational Social Science, Contributed July 2023 Explaining gendered retention patterns in academia Atlanta Conference on Science & Innovation Policy, Contributed May 2023 Women in Network Science & Diversify NetSci Satellite, Contributed July 2022 International Conference on Computational Social Science, Contributed July 2022 International Conference on the Science of Science & Innovation, Contributed June 2022 Accelerating deep neural networks International Memory Workshop, Invited May 2020 Towards detecting dyslexia in children's handwriting using neural networks American Handwriting Analysis Foundation, Invited Nov. 2019 June 2019 Computer Vision for Global Challenges Workshop, CVPR, Contributed AI for Social Good Workshop, ICML, Contributed June 2019

Posters

Explaining gendered retention patterns in academia

International Conference on Computational Social Science

July 2023

The elite undergraduate backgrounds of U.S. professors

International Conference on Computational Social Science

July 2022

International Conference on the Science & Innovation

June 2022

Towards detecting dyslexia in children's handwriting using neural networks

AI for Social Good Workshop, NeurIPS Dec. 2019
AI for Social Good Workshop, ICML, Best poster award. [Poster] June 2019

Teaching

F 2019	Professional Development Teaching Assistant
1 2013	1 Totessional Development Teaching Assistant

IBM Research Upskilling Class on Deep Learning

Sp 2019 Lead Teaching Assistant

CS C343: Introduction to Data Structures & Algorithms

Sp 2018, F 2018 **Teaching Assistant**

CS C343: Introduction to Data Structures & Algorithms

F 2016, Sp 2017, F 2017 **Teaching Assistant**

CS C241: Discrete Mathematics for Computer Science

Undergraduate Research Mentoring

•	Joanna Mendy	CU Sociology & Political Science	2022-2023
•	Maria Martinez	CU Political Science & Ethnic Studies	Summer 2022
•	Swag Das	CU Computer Science	Spring 2022
•	Jordan Roos	CU Biomedical Engineering	Spring 2022

Service

•	CU Computer Science PhD Application Mentor	2020-present
•	You're @ CU Graduate Student Mentor	2022
•	McNair Scholars Graduate Student Mentor	2021-2022
•	CU Engineering Mentor for Underrepresented First-Year Undergraduates	2020-2022
•	Lead Ambassador, IU Luddy School of Informatics, Computing & Engineering	2016-2019
•	Software Development Intern, Serve IT Nonprofit Technology Clinic	2016-2017

Reviewing: eLife, Social Policy & Administration, Proceedings of the ACM on Interactive, Mobile, Wearable and Ubiquitous Technologies

Other Professional Activities

Attendee.

•	Summer Institute in Computational Social Science at Duke University	2022
	Selected participant. Funded by the Russell Sage Foundation.	
•	Grad Cohort for Women Workshop, Computing Research Association (CRA)	2021